Hello, AP
US History students.  Here is the
second period in three
minutes.  The second
period
focuses on
colonization from 1607 to
1754.  The French
founded small
settlements, such as
Quebec and New Orleans
, along the Great Lakes
and the Mississippi River.
They maintained
friendly relations with
indigenous peoples,
which helped them
profit
from the fur trade.
The French also
focused on
conversion to
Catholicism, but
through peaceful
Jesuit missionaries.
The Dutch were similar
to the French,
establishing the colony of
New Amsterdam for
trade.  But
English
colonization
was characterized by
mass migration,
beginning with
Jamestown in 1607
.  Jamestown was
founded as a
joint stock
company to
generate profits
for investors and the
British Crown.
Tobacco plantations
became the basis of the
economy and
social structure of the
Chesapeake
Bay colonies, which
included Virginia and
Maryland.  But while
settlers in
Virginia were
largely
motivated by profit
, Maryland was
founded as a
haven for
Catholics.  Like the
Chesapeake region, the
southern colonies of
North Carolina,
South Carolina, and
Georgia also
grew cash
crops, but
focused more on
rice, indigo, and sugar.
South Carolina
had the highest
concentration of
African slaves
of any colony,
leading to
violent uprisings,
such as the Stono Rebellion
, and the passage of harsh
slavery laws.    The
New England colonies,
such as Massachusetts,
were founded for
religious reasons
.  This was
demonstrated by
the sermon of
Puritan leader
John Winthrop, "
City on a Hill."  These
strict religious
communities consisted
of tightly knit
towns centered around a
church.    The
New England colonies
had rocky
soil, unsuitable
for plantation
agriculture.  Because of
this, their economy
depended on
fishing,
logging, and
trade through
port cities like
Boston.  However, they
expelled dissidents
such as Ann Hutchinson and
Roger Williams, who
later founded Rhode
Island.  The middle
colonies were the
most ethnically and
economically
diverse.  In 1664,
England captured
Dutch New
Amsterdam and
renamed it
New York.  William
Penn founded the
Pennsylvania Colony
on Quaker
ideals such as
freedom and equality.
They had friendlier
relations with Native
Americans and
were generally
opposed to slavery.  These
colonies
were also called the "
breadbasket" because
they earned their living by
growing grain
.  They also
profited
from shipping and
logging.  Due to
rapid population growth,
tensions grew between
colonists and
indigenous tribes
over land and
resources.  This led
to violent
conflicts, such as
Powhatan's Rebellion
or King
Philip's War, which often
had devastating
consequences for
indigenous populations.
Over time, the 13 colonies
developed their
own cultures.  This
was partly due to
geographical distance
and unique
landscape, but also
due to a unique
tradition of
self-government.  This
was evident through the
Mayflower Compact
, the Virginia House of
Burgesses, and the
Fundamental
Orders of Connecticut.    The
colonial economy
was based on the theory of
mercantilism,
according to which a country
becomes richer
by exporting more
than it has to
import.
In an attempt
to control
colonial trade
, the Crown passed
a series of Navigation
Acts, but these
were enforced
nominally through
a policy known as
"salvage negligence"
.  And in the 1730s,
there was a religious
revival known
as the First Great
Awakening,
led by Jonathan
Edwards and George
Whitfield.  Edwards
attracted people to
the church by instilling
fear with sermons
like "Sinners in
the Hands of an Angry
God," while
Whitfield inspired
emotional conversions
at mass meetings,
so the colonists
began to
question the authority of the church
, which also
led them to
question the authority of the
British Crown.
One example of
colonists
challenging
British authority
was
Bacon's Rebellion.  Nathaniel
Bacon led a
violent
uprising of poor
farmers in 1676
against the royal
governor of
Virginia, William
Berkeley, over
unfair
treatment and
lack of protection
from attacks by Native
Americans.  This
demonstrated the
growing
tensions between
settlers and
colonial
leaders.  This
rebellion also
contributed to the shift from the
use of
indentured
servants to the labor of
enslaved
Africans in the
Virginia colony.  Thanks for
watching, and if you
need more
help with A Push, like
tutorials,
timelines, and recap videos
,
be sure
to check out the ultimate
review packet.